Welcome back to "Let's build a compiler".
In this episode we will
build in our language the minus, times and division operators.
My name is Yankee and I hope you have a lot of fun.
Initially, we will specify our compiler,
which will as well be known by the name "CompilerTest".
Then we'll go to our examples, that we want to be able to
copy one line as sample
and put down here some examples.
In fact: What will we build?
Firstly, we'll have a subtraction,
taking "3-2" for example,
then we will have an 1 as output.
Then we might as well build multiplication,
taking "2+3", so that we need "6" as output.
then Division, namely "6/2" as example of it,
so comes 3 as output.
Then, we can think later
on what happens if no result returns as output,
also, what should happened with "7/2"?
Typically, when we deal with integers
we cut the ".5" from behind,
Until this moment, we've worked only with integers,
later we naturally will have floating point types
but for the beginning we still with what we have
and the result stays 3, without the 0.5 behind.
Then one could naturally combine the operators:
For example, if we have: "8-2+5",
is really important to calculate first the "8-2" (making 6)
and thereafter "+5", so we'll have 11.
In place of "2+5", which would be 7
and so does "8-7", which would be 1.
The same happening to division, were we could take "8/2*4" as example.
"8/2" are 4, times 4 makes 16.
Here again, another thing outcomes,
if we calculate first the '2*4", it would be 8
and then we would have "8/8, naturally 1.
Then we can also combine subtraction with the multiplication:
We can take for example "2+3*3",
we should first calculate "3*3" (being 9), "+2" being 11,
if we would first calculate "2+3", then would be 5, times 3 would be 15,
that's another thing again.
and the same, once again, with the subtraction:
Like in the example "9-2*3":
"2*3" are 6 and "9-6" are 3.
In reverse, "9-2" would be 7, times 3 would be 21.
Then we save this and go forward...
Ah, for the first time we will see if our test has fails already.
Yes, we have many "Failures" here, 7 Failures,
these all are our new tests
and here at the top we have many "Token recognition error"s,
because ANTLR still not recognize all these operators over here.
So now we go next to our grammar
and we will continue with our new operators.
At first, we rename now some things in our grammar.
Because our "addition" rule will either way be expanded,
to make it contain not only additions,
but any math expression,
for this I call the "expression" rule
and then I will be using default English terms here,
because at the moment there is an incompatibility between German and English writing
and this is not good.
Otherwise, I like the idea where
with this number translate to the English
e is very unpractical, if there are too much German terms.
After we have this done...
After we have this done again
in our usual known way
I build our parser again,
pressing "F5" on parser,
then we go to the visitor
and adapt our terms,
this thing here is called naturally "right" now,
"ZahlContext" doesn't work anymore, now we name it "NumberContext"
with "Ctrl+Shift+0" we can fix the importations,
and we save again and we'll see later,
if our tests still correct or working badly like just before.
Yes, our first three tests are working
and the news, those, that we generated just now, aren't working.
We go back to our grammar
and start now with the improvements.
At first, we will build our "minus" operator.
We'll gona by here also copy our previous "plus" rule
and put an alternative for the "minus".
We call this "Minus",
we change the operator to "minus" here,
we save, we return again to the console,
we leave our parser generate anew,
go to the parser, press "F5",
we go over the visitor, behind the visitPlus
now we can insert a new "visitMinus" method,
it works similarly to "visitPlus",
Now, here I simply copy the template,
for the subtraction we only in place of "iadd" we name it "isub".
Wonderful, we close it and leave the test run once more.
What's the result?
In our minus test the "println(3-2) worked!
Hey! That was simple!
We want to see once again if it will be right together with the other operators.
So we copy again our previous rule too,
again for the division and multiplication,
our parser must be generated again with the old known command,
let's go to the parser with "F5",
we go to our visitor
and will implement the new "visit" method.
For division
The same again what we have had with minus,
just with "idiv" standing for i-divide
and then again another for multiplication
and we call the instructions "imul".
We save, leave our tests run
and what do we see here?
Eight of our tests worked, two doesn't.
Times worked, division worked,
that with the "7/2" also worked,
"8/2*4" worked too,
but, unfortunately these two didn't work.
And as you can see here: we have 11 waiting, but 15 retrieved,
obviously, the operator order was not properly observed here,
here it would have to calculate "2+3" first, making 5
and then times 3, making 15, and it's what we received here.
but, sadly, this is not what we wanted.
At this local it gives us a little Cliffhanger.
How we manage correctly the operators priorities,
so that our two remaining tests would work you will learn in the next episode.
In this episode we learned how to build minus
division and plus operators in the grammar
and how we generate combined instructions:
Further operators with sub-rules definitions
and combined instructions generation with new visit methods,
looks almost exactly like "visitPlus" method.
On our next episode we're expecting, as mentioned
the right order definition for the operators
and we expect later
variables, loops, conditional functions and much more.
Write me in the comments, for what you want for the next episodes.
Naturally, I would be flattered with comment replies:
What are the pluses and the minuses?
How do you take advantage of the videos?
Do you program along?
You use the videos for research about concrete problems?
Or do you watch the videos without any project, just for interest?
Thanks a lot to Gadarol, that permitted to record in his studio
and thank you very much for paying attention.
My name is Yankee, I hope you've had fun,
goodbye and see you later
for another: "Let's build a compiler".