Welcome back to "Let's build a compiler".
In the last episode we had successfully build
the minus, times, anda division for our language.
Sadly, we still have problems
like the operators having links one to another.
For example, the result from "2+3*3" was 15, instead of the expected 11.
In this episode we will show why this is so
and then expand our compiler, so it also solves this problem.
My name is Yankee and I wish you a lot of fun.
And now for understanding what the problem is
we want generate once the tree from ANTLR
to allow us to see "2+3*3".
For this we go over the console,
go to our parser's directory,
we take for us again the TestRig command from the last time
and then we'll execute println(2+3*3*);",
then Ctrl+D on Linux, Ctrl+Z on Windows
and then the tree is shown to us.
So, here you see our program now:
It has a "println" with an "expression"
and that "expression" from here consists of a multiplication and an addition.
You can se, that the addition stays down on our tree,
have gained priority.
That means, if we traverse here in Post-Order,
then we'd have 2, 3, plus, times.
Unfortunately, this is namely not what we wanted.
Can we fix this problem now?
Therefore, firstly, we'll observe again inside our grammar
and wonder us what should really happen.
We have here the expression "2+3*3".
And we want that this gonna be treated as it was "2+9".
This means we have first the 2, it is a "NUMBER"
and then we have one plus, also it's in the top rule here
and then comes of the right side from the plus calculation,
again, with an "times" expression.
Damn it, we unfortunately are not allowed,
the right part here can only, at this moment, be a "NUMBER".
What we do then?
Instead of "NUMBER" we always use he "expression",
within the right part from our plus
can be an "expression" and be also another "times".
This is naturally not the only thing that changed
this allow us a "times",
if I change this grammar part of "expression" for the right part,
then we have now by here, not simply
just a Token inside our label "right",
but also another "expression".
This naturally continues OK,
because our right part can also again be simply just a "NUMBER",
but our visitor must, in this way, adapt to our visitor.
We call now again to generate on the next time
from our "grammar" directory
our parser anew,
then, we go inside the parser in Eclipse with "F5",
thus, we open our visitor
and henceforth we adjust it.
Now he is like this, together with our other
visit methods we have here,
also as example with "visitPlus"
the "visitChildren" can can also return a "ldc".
Because we have down here a "visitNumber" method
and it already gives us the "ldc".
That's really elegant, because it means
we don't have to give the "ldc" in here anymore.
This yet comes from the "visitChildren" here to our under next.
We remove also the "ldc" from everywhere
and then we execute our test one more time.
And it has not changed anything in itself:
All the old test are still functional,
the new ones don't work until now.
Where are they?
We'll see our grammar once again:
We want here to continue the 2+3 for evaluation now
the plus that returns and the right part of the multiplication.
Yes, with a goofy execution, the ANTLR accepted the namely reverse:
ANTLR begins with a fact saying:
I have here a multiplication first
and this multiplication has a "2+3" child on the left
and then on the right only the 3.
And when we look straight inward the grammar,
we also see: in fact, it's ambiguous,
that can be seen as so or so.
How does ANTLR handle such a case?
It always takes the first rule above.
The rule above also have the biggest priority.
And we have with us at the moment:
The plus has highest priority.
That is naturally stupid,
because we want the opposite.
The multiplication operator must
have higher priority than the plus.
Also, we have to change these both rules.
Therefor, we generate again our parser anew,
going here with "F5"
and executing our tests.
So, what do the tests say?
In fact, it didn't work.
it suggests now that only a test remains,
namely, the "8/2*4" test.
One thing that you could have payed attention,
is natural to the division to have
a higher priority than the subtraction.
But this isn't everything.
Because here down in the Test, the error suggestion
doesn't return any subtraction.
This also can't be a problem for the test represented here.
The true problem for our test comes next,
because the multiplication and division are
seen on the same level of our operators ranking.
We can write here now:
"Times or Division",
and with the operators stablish the same height
and truly, the ANTLR would be in this case
solve the operators from the left to the right
and make it right.
But we can't work anymore as well as we want with our labels.
When we want to step forward the labels in which we are working,
we should think in another way.
One possible way would be:
Put the division before the multiplier in priority.
Then you see the general look.
And now we respectively evaluate the division before de multiplication
and the subtraction before the addition.
Does this also work?
Here is an example for it:
Let say: we want "2*8/4" as refractive.
So, this is will independent, if we want to calculate in this way:
"2*8" are 16, divided by 4 are 4.
Or let's say: "2*(8/4)"
and we'll calculate first the "8/4",
because in this case, "8/4" would be 2 and "2*2", still, 4.
Furthermore, the multiplication operator holds,
in contrast with the division operator, the commutative property.
We'll prove one more time
if the test operators order now goes through.
We'll generate also our new parser,
we go here with "F5"
and we let our test run.
And Hurra, it says that everything is fine,
all our tests worked.
Just, one more time for demonstration, I want now
show you the tree, how it looks.
Also, we take our TestRig again,
go to the first folder with our parser
and extract the TestRig out,
giving now another:
"println(2+3*3)"
and it shows the tree.
As you see:
Now is the "plus" that stays on top, and the times down there
and the things even more in the bottom are those we first calculate,
because we solve the tree from bottom to the top,
we also calculate "3*3" and then "+2".
In this episode we have learned,
how we can write our parser rules for calculations,
that also in the chain calculations with more operators
can detect any complex expression.
We learned alo, that through
the order of sub-rules
can change the operators precedence ranking.
Which features do you want to see next?
What are your questions and requests?
About which problems and solutions have you stumbled,
working with a compiler?
Write me in the comments!
Leave me a thumb up here, if you liked this video
and sign my channel, with it you don't loose any episode.
Thanks a lot to Gadarol,
that allowed me to make the recordings in his studio.
Thank you very much for you attention,
goodbye and until the next time,
for the next episode of: "Let's build a compiler".